[Music]
this program is brought to you by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu
and if you were to calculate the
gaussian
curvature remember in two Dimensions the
gaussian the curvature is just a um it
just has one component only has one
independent component and it's the
curvature scalar if you were to
calculate the curvature
scalar then on the outer rim of the
Taurus here you would find it's positive
and in the inner region here you would
find it's negative and is in such a way
that the integral of the curvature over
the Taurus is
zero okay and that's true for any object
which has the topology of a Taurus here
I'm going to I'm going to modify
it
it's still a
Taurus we can modify it into a uh into a
coffee cup or whatever it's still a
Taurus what I've done is add some
negative curvature over here and some
positive curvature out here but without
changing the integral of the curvature
so there's a theorem about the integral
of the curvature the integral of the
curvature is called the oiler number and
it's related to the number of holes and
handles
on the other hand if I put another hole
in
here then I would change the integrated
curvature and this cannot be
flattened this has an integrated
curvature which is negative more
negative than
positive
so you
unfold so it's flat M
because Z yeah that doesn't Pro you can
unfold it it just uh here the integrated
curvature is not zero and moreover the
integrated curvature is something which
only depends on the
topology that's a theorem that's o
theorem or gusis theorem wait wait that
the integrated curvature in
here is equal to um uh the integrated
curvature for a sphere in certain units
is + one
the integrated curvature for any
Taurus is
zero the integrated T the integrated
curvature for a Taurus with two holes in
it is minus one integrated curvature
with three
holes minus 2 and so it
goes uh the number of holes is called
the oiler number so the integrated
curvature is related to the oiler number
I can't remember the oil number the
integrated is it uh yeah well the oiler
number is related to the number of holes
and
handles and the integrated curvature
only depends on the topology it doesn't
change if you put a bulge on it it
doesn't change if you put a bulge on the
sphere and so forth good so here's what
we
know the integrated curvature of this is
zero the integrated curvature of a plane
is clearly Z Z because its curvature is
everywhere zero and so this is the only
one that would have any chance of being
flattened the integrated curvature of
this cannot be flattened because it's
always going to be minus one yeah is it
possible to put a metric on the Taurus
yeah that's everywhere zero
no everywhere zero I mean in other words
make it make it flat not the not not the
making metric zero doesn't make it flat
well I mean picking a
metric where curvature where the
curvature is zero yes yes yes yes yes
you can put a metric that's the point
you can put a metric on a Taurus which
makes it everywhere's flat okay now
suppose I have a sphere and I take one
point out of a sphere that doesn't make
a c out of it I know but can I make that
everywhere
flat can I choose a metric for the for
the sphere minus a point where which
would make it ah can you choose you
you're not going to choose the standard
metric of the sphere the question is can
you choose a yes you can then it be a
sphere less one point becomes the
infinite plane and the way to see
that in other words it's a question can
you map a sphere to a plane can you map
a sphere into a plane or or one to one
correspondence of a sphere onto a plane
if you can then you can just use the
metric on the sphere that it inherits
from the plane now you can almost do
that there are many ways to do it of
course you take the
sphere and you imagine that it's tangent
to a
plane it's it's just sitting it's
resting on a plane okay you take every
point on the sphere and you map it to a
point on the plane by doing the
following you go to the North Pole
here's the North Pole here's the South
Pole and you draw a straight line from
the North Pole through the point in
question p over here and you continue it
until you hit the
plane okay every point on the sphere
gets mapped to a point in the plane in
this way the South Pole gets mapped
right to the point where the sphere is
resting every Point gets mapped to a
point on the plane except for one point
which is that PO the North Pole if you
include the point at Infinity if you
imagine one extra
point which is really the point and
infinity and of course it seems odd to
think of infinity as a point Infinity
that way doesn't seem to be the same but
suppose you identify them all then
that's equivalent to the sphere so
here's what you can do you can place a
metric on the plane the standard metric
on the plane the x² plus p y^2 and say
every pair of points every pair of
neighboring points has a certain
distance between them as given by the
simpleminded metric on the uh on the
plane and then map those two points to
two points on the sphere I don't think I
did it very well but simply give them
the same
distance as the two points on the plane
had in that way you will have a metric
which
um flattens the sphere
but this point at the North Pole here
since it corresponds to points very very
far away this metric the distance
between this point let's say this point
and that point what's the distance
between that point and that point it's
going to be huge or or infinite right
this point Maps out to
Infinity this point over here next to it
maps to some other place which is finite
so that means that the metric the
components of the metric up near the
North Pole here are going to go to
Infinity the components of this peculiar
metric which flattens the sphere are
going to diverge with the North Pole so
so an ant on the sphere their measuring
rods would shrink as they head to the
North Pole and when they measure
triangles they'd always get 180°
yeah all right
where if they made triangles by the
rules of constructing
geodesics the rules of geodesics will no
longer be great circles on here or they
may be but if they are they're actually
uh actually they
are
uh I think every um I have to think
about it I have question I have go back
to the before you Chang the two vehicles
together there any I saw is there
any meaning to that it could be the two
strings coming together and
emerging I'm sure we could find one if
you triy hard enough off hand I can't
think of any
okay yeah yeah is it possible to uh uh
Define a a for transformation from a a
two space to three space
not
a continuous
one not a continuous
one
um because you know for example if you
no two space for a sphere on the board
uh you can it appears you can M that
into a flat free space
no the sphere cannot be the sphere
cannot be mapped depends on what you
mean
by um every point in a you def find a
curvature with some kind of tensor you
know that defines the sphere um same
like like what you're doing there can
you map that not from two space but a
free space because again embedded within
a free space no no way it's indifferent
to you can place a sphere and embedded
in three space that's not the same as
mapping it well mapping it into onto one
to one when I say mapping I mean one to
one uh correspondence one to one right
every point in the three in the
three-dimensional space corresponds to a
unique
point on two dimensional space and vice
versa that is possible but it's not
possible to do in a continuous fashion
in fact it's the only way you can do it
is by scrambling up the points in a
monstrously complicated way so we could
give you a rule for uh here's a
rule two-dimensional space is
characterized by
[Music]
um uh by pairs of real numbers right
pairs of real numbers we can write down
the first real number and let's let's
take the region from 0er to one just for
Simplicity so I take a two-dimensional
square and I'm going to map a
two-dimensional Square onto a um
one-dimensional line in each case it's
going to go from 0er to
one okay can we do that can we really do
that
yes take the two-dimensional point and
characterize it by a real number a real
number means a decimal
37941 6 blah blah blah uh if it's a if
it's a rational number then it's a
repeating decimal if it's an irrational
number it's a non-re repeating decimal
and so forth
uh we need two of them
846 blah blah blah blah
blah and
now take a new number that we're going
to make out of
them by interwining the Numbers here
with the numbers here so first we pick
the point three then we go down to here
eight then we go up to here seven then
we go down to here four then we go up to
nine then six you see what the pattern
is I've taken a one from here followed
it by this up to here followed by that
and so forth this is a unique number
given a point
here there's a unique real number that
you can make by this construction and
furthermore given this real number here
I can take it apart and disassemble it
put the three up here the eight here the
seven here and so forth so for every one
of for every one of these which means
every pair of real numbers there is by
this construction a unique real number
so long as you omit zero right what's
that so long as you emit the zero point
why why
no have a zero point
here and it maps to the zero point
here
okay right but if you were to take a
point like
this and a close by Point Let's sorry
this is excuse me um let's take two
numbers here which are close to each
other let's see no I don't want these
two numbers to be close to each other I
want to take pairs of real points here's
one and here's another one and we take
them to be close to each other in
general they will not be close to each
other on the line so will be it will be
close
because if the differences are out in
the out in out in the F ends the
different the changes in in the image
will be out of far well let's
see won't be differentiable yeah it
certainly won't be differentiable
certainly will not be differentiable no
I think it's always going to be very
very scrambled there will always be
points which are close together here
which are far from here
I think it's I think it's I think it's
the I think it's um say it
again
38 you could take1 and then Z with a
whole string of NES those are very
[Music]
close so there's always there's always
going to be a lot of scrambling you
can't map it in any kind of continuous
fashion
uh and so in particular functions which
are smooth on this plane here are going
to be if mapped to here we take a
function of X and Y
here and we reconstruct from it a
function on the line how do we do it
well if we want to know what the value
of the function is at Point whatever it
is we reconstruct from this number here
the real number the pair of real numbers
go to that point and take F and just
bring it down to here that function is
going to be wildly uh varying
neighboring values of X here will
correspond to wildly in general
Divergent values of um not diverent in
sense of infinite it also depends on
your starting point whether you start
with the
three yeah it does this is interesting I
got I got a question about curvature mhm
um if you use
um
U so so so needless to say in eventally
we're not going to consider this a
proper reasonable coordinate
transformation if you have if you're
describ 's a space with with geodesic
coordinates then the then the
Christ Christ let me just let me say
exactly what that means so
not for your benefit but for the rest
of I think by geodesic coordinates we
mean we have some curved space and at
some point strictly at some point we
construct some geodesic like that we
construct a perpendicular geodesic like
that we call that the X and Y AIS for
example and then any
point we
can any nearby point Point close to this
point over here we can assign a
coordinate we can assign a pair of
coordinates by dropping perpendicular
geodesics to here and perpendicular
geodesics to
here right and then
assign this point the coordinates equal
to this distance and that distance is
that what you mean by geodesic
coordinates yeah understand symbol yeah
those are those are the coordinates
those are the coordinates
in which the metric tensor at this point
is Delta i j or Delta MN and in which
the first derivatives of the metric are
equal to
zero okay there are the coordinates
which sort of match most closely to a
flat coordinate system over yeah but but
and but and so some of the terms of the
remon tensor go away it's probably true
some of them may me because they're
they're just the they're just the
products of the cryst symbols but the
but other terms
theives that's right that's right um
wondering also go away no they won't go
away they won't go oh sorry yes of
course in general of course they will go
away yeah the CH the christopal symbols
at this point are all zero yeah but they
don't but but the derivatives with
respect oh I'm sorry sorry sorry the
christopal symbols are zero the
derivatives of the christopal symbol
will not be zero but you're right you're
right there are two terms and the remon
tensor has two kinds of terms it has
derivatives of the christopal symbols
and it will have plus quadratic things
in the christopal symbols just
schematically these of course will be
zero why because at that at that point
only at this point at that point the
christopal symbols will be zero why
because the christopal symbols all
contain derivatives of the G's and if
those are Z
these are zero on the other hand these
things here will contain second
derivatives of
G and those won't be zero and I was
wondering if you get any insight into
the re tens by looking at that
particular case it's
possible um I wouldn't be surprised
uh good so what you want to do is to
relate the both the remont tensor the
reachy tensor and the scal Cur the Scala
curvature you would want to relate it to
the various second derivatives of the
metric so it's the second derivatives of
the metric which come in
I very likely there is some uh some
picture that you can make from it from
this
construction but it would involve the
second derivatives of the metric now
what kind of nice geometric picture do
you have about the second derivatives of
the metric yeah right but that's but
nevertheless it's correct that the
remont tensor in those
coordinates simply involves the
collection of second derivatives of the
metric and that's it doesn't involve
first derivatives and so you can
reconstruct it from
those and maybe vice versa also that You
Could reconstruct this or a lot of
information about the second derivatives
of the metric from the remont
tensor
okay any other any other
questions special relativity special
relativity yeah we're going to talk
about that an example
of first of all GE geodesic minimizes
the U or maximizes the proper time for
okay you did an example where you uh
have flat space and actually put small
be you show that if you maximize the the
path maximize of the proper time is the
path minimizes the kinetic energy which
is Maxim minimizes the energy which is
they show those
for that in a more General sense say it
again can can you do you showed that
those two were equivalent that the path
yeah well okay but you have to
understand that the kinetic energy is
related to the path length with a
negative sign right
uh right okay so so it's not it's not a
crazy thing thing that minimizing one
maximizes the other uh can you do that
in general uh if you just had a bunch of
say a density mass no other forces is
gravitation and show that the the
geodesic that you get is equivalent to
minimizing uh
lent Min minimizing the lran for the
point
particle yeah what you can't show
because it's not generally true is that
every geodesic is an absolute minimum of
the distance it's a it's a local minimum
you know what the difference
is
um I know reg function the difference
between local and Global yeah maximum
minimum um oh if you just take any small
variation it's it's it's a minimum
that's right if you take any small
variation it's a minimum but you may be
able to find some large deviation which
find some path of uh you got a whole
colle yeah yeah you may have more than
one geodesic connecting pairs of points
in particular in fact as a rule you do
in general you
do
ring well for example but uh a simple
example would be you take a nice
symmetric
Hill in two dimensional
space uh let's make a very high hill now
I'm not talking about space time I'm
just talking about ordinary space just
to illustrate the point that there can
be more than one
geodesic
uh typically there will be a geodesic
between here and here let's plot it
horizontally so I have a contour map for
this thing here's the contour map for it
big
hill typically there'll be a jidc which
um
will it'll find a compromise if I went
all around
here that would cost me some pathway
in avoiding the hill on the other hand
if I go over right over the top of the
hill there's a great big distance there
around so there typically will be a
geodesic which will find a compromise
and go somewhat up the hill but not very
not very far up the hill just think
about taking a string attaching it to
here and here and pulling it
tight all right it'll climb partway up
the
hill okay there'll also be another
geodesic by symmetry which goes around
the other way I'm assuming these two
points are symmetrically related to the
hill over here in fact there's even a
third one and the third one goes right
through the center
here but it probably somehow is a local
M that's a local maximum of the distance
it's a
geodesic by virtue of the fact that it
it it's um the tangent Vector is co
variantly constant it is not a geodesic
if what you meant was a minimum of the
distance between two points it happens
to be a
maximum uh it has the peculiar property
that if you had a string and you pulled
it tight and you kept it perfectly
symmetric you would pull it right over
the top of the hill and it would form
you know go right over the top of the
hill but if you displaced it a little
bit it would be unstable and it would
slide off the top of the hill so it's
actually a maximum of the uh uh of the
length local what's that only a local
Max oh oh yeah yeah of course it's only
a local yes it's a local ma maximum but
it is a jesic according to the official
rules of geodesics it's a
geodesic uh where the official rule
means that that the tangent Vector is
covariant
constant so good those good questions
any more stable and
unstable well you can have a maximum or
a minimum of the distance yeah if it's a
maximum then it's an unstable yeah what
it means what that means for the motion
of a particle or something is another
story but uh that's so what you did back
then is you actually showed that you
didn't even do the calcul of variations
you just took the proper time expression
and and you and you broke it up can you
do that in more
generality just to say a mass
distribution and show that you come up
with a geodesic
equation uh the geodes equation will
always be the equation that the tangent
Vector is covariant constant okay now
what are what are you asking now um I'm
asking the you got two calculus
variations problems one says minimize
the Leon the other says maximize the
proper time and you show those for
equivalent in a special in special
relativity the flat space and and and
that's that's that's almost a
definition the question is what's the
definition of the action well
sorry we
compared um variation of distance with
variation of
action variation
yeah variation action well that's just
because by definition the action for
a particle moving in space Time by
definition is minus its
mass
times the
uh the town times the proper
time so that's essentially a uh a
definition right and you can get the
lran from
this we could do that I mean it uh it
doesn't take very long it's pretty easy
to do let's do it
good let let's let's do it and you can
work out lr's equations and show that
they are the same as demanding that the
covariant derivative of the tangent
Vector is
zero okay
so the definition of the action along a
trajectory is minus the mass times the
proper time along the trajectory and the
proper time squared along a differential
little piece of it here is d^ s equal g
i j let's say
gmn of position won't bother writing
what it is uh D DXM
dxn good all right now all we have to do
is take the square root of this that's D
to and then integrate it to find the
total path length from here to here so
the total path
length is the
integral this is kind of a funny thing
to see an integral of a square root with
a DX DX but I'll make sense of it for
you in a moment G
MN
DXM
dxn minus M that's the minus M which
appears here right that's the
action now what can can I do to it to
make it look more familiar pick one of
the coordinates a Time coordinate let's
pick time xnot and let's call it time uh
this is G mu new mu new mu
new and so forth okay and uh let's write
this whole thing out it first of all has
the space likee components in other
words when mu and new are both space
likee then
there's the mixed space time
components plus twice
GM
DXM DX knot why did I put a two
there because GM because it's symmetric
there's an equal one from GM and from g
m all right so I just wrote it this way
g m DX M DX not
and then the last term is plus G KN DX
DX now let's call DX not let's call it t
let's call it x t so this just becomes
DT okay now let's divide and multiply by
DT squ by DT let's divide multiply here
by
DT and now divide this whole thing by DT
but if I do it inside the square
root that means dividing by DT 2qu
right if I want to divide by DT but then
I want to put the DT into the square
root I make it dt^ squar okay let's look
at what we have DXM by DT * dxn by DT
what is
that
that's the product of
velocities this is the MTH component of
the Velocity this is the nth component
of the Velocity here we have 1 DT
cancels and we have DXM by
DT that's also a component that's
something linear in the velocity and
what about this here what did I do
here yeah I forgot to call this DT
s but I'm dividing it by dt^ 2 so this
goes
away well now I have something that
really looks like a l grangian here it
is it involves the positions remember
the G's depend on
X we have dependence on position and
components of the
Velocity it's a rather complicated lran
it's not like like the good old
non-relativistic lran which only has 1
12 MX do^ S Plus V ofx everything occurs
in the square root that's a big
nuisance particularly when you start
differentiating it but you take this
lran which depends on the velocities and
the coordinates and you just do the oila
lrange equations and that will give you
the equations of motion for the
particle it is also the same thing as
minimizing maximizing making stationary
the uh the proper distance or the proper
time and would allow you to construct an
energy function and so forth so this is
the lran for uh uh for a point particle
moving in an arbitrary gravitational
field okay you can take this you can
work out Lan's
equations and prove that they are the
same as let's see what they're the same
as okay it's a little bit it's a little
bit of a
nuisance for the following reason the
equation for your geodesic in terms of
the tangent Vector has
been DC X by DS squared or D
squared plus anybody remember what else
there
is
[Music]
that's the equation for geodesic now the
nuisance part of it is that this is
going to give you an equation where the
independent variable is going to be time
you're going to work this out and you're
going to write equations for X as a
function of time
so the equations are going to be second
order equations good
old oil lrange equations and they're
going to involve things like DX by DT
whereas this repres this is in terms of
DX by D too so what you have to do is
you have to convert everything to T
notation instead of town notation so
let's for example say this is a space-
likee component let's call it
m
m and the other ones stay the way they
are all right the first thing we'd have
to do is deal with this guy here this is
DX M by D to D by D
to but we simply use the rule that
differentiating with respect to too is
the same as differentiating with respect
to T and then multiplying by DTD
to but what is DTD to DTD
to
it's not
one it's not one we have to remember
what T is in terms of
to uh T and well we have to we have to
work out what DT by D to is but we know
what it is uh
the all right let's work it out the to^
squar is equal to um g dt^ 2 plus G1 dx1
squ blah blah blah blah
blah and then we simply divide this by
d^ squ 1 d
squar d
to same thing sort of thing and then we
solve for DT by DT we just solve for DT
by DT that tells us what DT by DT is and
it's just some complicated thing
involving the metric and the velocities
so something complicated but known goes
in here for DT by for DT by D
to and then we do the same thing again d
by DT d by D to is d by DT times DT by D
to do the same thing here gamma dot dot
dot and instead of writing DX by DS we
write DX by DT DT by this is to sorry
how getting myself mixed
up we just rework it so that it becomes
an equation of motion for X as a
function of time it's easy to do it's
just Elementary calculus and it's the
same equation as this let's not uh do it
it's more of a nuisance than anything
but the point is the logic logic is that
the principle of least action and the
principle of least proper time of the
same thing in any
metric so if you plug in a metric you'll
automatically retrieve aian for the
motion of the
particle notice this G not not
here um let's let's do a simple
example let's suppose that only G KN was
interesting by interesting it means
different than uh different than the
flat space
metric let's suppose that g
was different what is g not in flat
space
time one
right one all right let's leave let's
let's simplify these by going to Flat
space time then what's
gmn Delta MN
right no gmn Del Delta MN or minus Delta
MN all right so this becomes essenti
the XM do the XM
squar I may have the sign wrong we may
need a minus sign this one I'll take to
be zero in flat space time GM not is
just zero so let's forget this and then
we have
G not of
X okay supposing
that have I missed
anything I did miss what did I miss I
missed
something I think I missed the term
which is DT
by DT by dt^
oh no that's here right yeah that's here
that's here that's just one that's just
one except I don't want to make that
approximation I want to let G vary so
let's Let It vary a little bit let's Let
It vary and call it one plus something
small so let's call it Delta G
KN all right so this is close to the N
this is close to the um Newtonian
approximation the only thing that's not
uh absolutely Newtonian the only thing
that's not absolutely flat space here is
that g might depend on X all right now
suppose the velocity is small
the velocity is small how do you expand
out
something like this how do you expand
out what do we have we have square T of
1 plus something
small this is one plus something
small right it's one plus something
small and the something small consists
of Delta G kn and the square of the
Velocity okay so what's what's the rule
for one plus square of 1 plus s 1 plus s
over2 okay so let's work it
out first of all we get minus M I'm
making a mess of this Blackboard but
let's keep going minus
M times now it's 1 + S over2 let's start
with 1
and now plus s over2 so what's S
over2 Plus Delta G
not over
two minus let's just call it X do^ 2ar
over two that's this term over here
H
okay do I have a it all right yeah okay
so the first term is just Why is it
minus
M oh it is minus M it's actually correct
minus M the first term is
minus
M right the next term is minus Delta g/
2 and then plus MX do^ 2/
2 what's this term well that that's very
familiar it's
just mv^ s 1 half MV squ what's this
term over here this is not the energy
incidentally this is the
lran the lran is related to the energy
by changing the sign of the potential
energy these two are potential
energies these two don't depend on
velocities their potential energy so
basically yeah MW oh M here right yeah
okay
so in terms of energy you would change
the sign of these two the first term
what would that
be doesn't matter in the energy no it
doesn't matter but what would it
be yeah it's the energy when the
particle has no motion and if I kept all
the speeds of light this would just be
minus mc^ s
why minus mc^ s because it's in the L
grangian not the uh not the energy the
energy you change the sign here what's
this one over
here it's a potential energy but now we
remember something we come back to
something familiar that the
gravitational potential normally we
would have I think it's m uh minus the
gravitational potential here so minus M
* the gravitational potential is just
Delta G KN over
two minus or plus I think I think with a
plus if I uh no I think with a minus if
I remember I I I always lose track of
the
sign uh M with an
M so what do we find we find the
equation that says that the
gravitational
potential uh is just equal to Delta G
g/
two now why Delta G KN do you remember
earlier we identified G not with uh with
G not over two with
f you remember that equation right why
do I write Delta G not
KN well the point is that we don't
really identify g with f we identified G
with f plus a constant it was the
derivatives of it was the derivatives of
G KN that we identified with the
derivatives of fi so we can add a
constant to G not and Delta G not just
means the deviation from the constant so
this is just a good old equation that we
had relating G to the gravitational
potential so you know you can you can
work with these equations um it wasn't
my goal in this class to spend a lot of
time working with these equations but
just mainly show you what they
are uh and of course they're much harder
than Newton's equations in the sense not
conceptually but in the sense that
whenever you have a square root to start
differentiating uh you're going to have
trouble so solving the equations is more
difficult but conceptually it's just the
same Oiler lrange equations that uh okay
where were we
Let's uh let's get started I did want I
did want
tonight to study black holes a little
bit the black hole metric actually this
was a good starting point but let's
uh let's just go through the schwar
shield black
hole now before we do that it's very
important to understand the concept of
an accelerated reference frame frame in
relativity an accelerated reference
frame is something which can have
meaning in special relativity or in
general
relativity and we begin with special
relativity in particular The Accelerated
reference frame is simply the reference
frame in ordinary special relativity as
seen by an accelerated Observer okay but
it's a little bit different it's a
little more subtle than it is in uh in
normal uh normal physics normal
Newtonian physics all right let's draw
SpaceTime here's
SpaceTime here's a light cone light
travels on 45° axis time is vertically
upward X goes out of the Blackboard this
way and y and z are only going wrong for
the ride we don't even need to think
about them they stick out of the
Blackboard but we're not going to play
very much with them all right now if you
remember an accelerated reference frame
in nutonian mechanics is one whose
coordinates are curved and they're
parabolas the're parabolas all of which
are sort of parallel to each other and
they just correspond to uh to the
acceleration of the motion of an
observer at rest in the moving frame so
at rest in the moving frame means moving
along one of these lines and that
Observer is an accelerated Observer
right uh notice one point well that's
that's uh that is what an accelerated
Observer is the acceleration is uniform
we assume the acceleration is
uniform and that means at any given time
if that Observer measures his own
acceleration and you can measure
acceleration you know you can feel
acceleration acceleration has an
uncomfortable
effect the acceleration all along here
is constant so that poor Observer who is
being accelerated with 25 G's of
acceleration is uncomfortable but
equally uncomfortable at all times
including times at which he's coming in
from far
away all right what kind of
observer in special relativity
corresponds to a uniformly accelerated
Observer it's one who feels the same
amount of acceleration at all times you
might think again that that's a
parabola in other words x equals let's
say uh constant X Plus t plus uh
acceleration * T ^2 acceleration over 2
* T
^2 well that's going to quickly make
that Accel that Observer move faster
than the speed of light remember with a
uniform acceleration velocity is equal
to acceleration time time so if you wait
long enough
uh you'll be moving with faster than the
speed of light that can't be what a real
accelerated reference frame is anybody
moving faster than the speed of light
feels something very very different than
what we feel and I I don't know what it
is okay so that can't be the right
idea the right
idea is a
hyperbola I'll explain why in a minute
an observer moving along a
hyperbola in special relativity is a
uniformly accelerated reference frame
now you can take that hyperbola to be
the hyperbola
x^2 minus t
^2 is equal to a
constant x^2 - t^2 equal a constant is a
hyperbola and it's a hyperbola of radius
let's call it c^ s it's a hyperbola of
radius i c in other words the distance
from the origin here at closest approach
this is at closest approach the distance
of the hyperbola is
C
now a hyperbola like this is Loren
invariant that means if you do a loren
transformation the hyperbola goes into
itself how do I know that I know that
because x^2 - t ^2 is an invariance of a
loren transformation we've gone through
this several times x^2 - t^2 is the
thing which doesn't change when you do a
lench
transformation in other words if I do a
lench transformation and I have a point
at which x² minus t ^2 = c^2 if I Loren
transform it after the Loren transform
it will still be on the same
hyperboloid the mathematics of this is
almost the
same as saying you have a circle which
would be x^2 + y^2 equal a constant and
saying that a rotation preserves the
circle a rotation about the origin
preserves the circle in the same way if
you do a loren
transformation this Curve will simply
slide into
itself that curve is Lorent
invariant and that means what's going on
at this point over here is as far as the
observ moving along here is exactly the
same as what's going on over here he
feels the same thing here as he feels
here as he feels here and so forth the
mathematics is very similar to saying
that somebody going in a circle would
feel the same thing here as here as here
as here as here there's a symmetry to
the problem and the Symmetry is such
that somebody traveling along this
trajectory will feel a
constant influence of the of the
acceleration at all
times okay that's the idea of a
uniformly
accelerated object in special relativity
now does it ever exceed the speed of
light what are the asmp tootes of this
hyperbola it's
asmic its ASM tootes are simply the like
cones it never gets up to the L cone it
never exceeds the speed of light it just
ASM totically gets closer and closer to
the speed of
light that's what a uniformly
accelerated uh object is in special
relativity something which is
approaching the speed of light with
uniform proper
acceleration proper acceleration means
the acceleration in the observer's rest
frame as the Observer is being
accelerated that observer in his own
frame of
reference senses always identical
acceleration Point by Point as he moves
along very very much like an observer
moving in a circle would experience the
same acceleration moving around in a
circle okay so this is what is called
a uh uniformly accelerated object a
uniformly accelerated reference frame
is really just you start at tal 0 here's
tal
0 and you mark off a bunch of meter
sticks and then you let each meter stick
whoops I didn't draw that very well move
on its own on its own
hyperboloid on its own
hyperbola and that becomes a uniformly
accelerated reference
frame but what that means if this
hyperbola here is x^2 - t ^2 = c^2 let's
call it 1 let's say this is 1
m 1
meter meter stick the end of the 1 meter
meter stick is at x^2 minus t ^2 = 1
what about the 2 metum stick what's its
equation x² minus t ^2
equals what do you want to write four
2^2 x^2 - t
^2 = 9 and so
forth okay that's a uniformly
accelerated family a family of uniformly
accelerated ends of meter
sticks now what about
time time along
these meter sticks ticks off along here
and it corresponds a good this is a
definition a definition of time is to do
the same kind of lorence transformation
on this line here to move the line
forward from one time to the next time
along each of these
hyperboloids that would look like
this here would be
time
remember when you do a loren
transformation the surface of constant
time the surface of
simultaneity what an observer calls
simultaneous gets tilted so what we're
doing is we're making a series of Loren
Transformations along this trajectory to
make them go faster and faster and
faster and
faster and the surface of simultaneity
is getting more and more
tilted oh I'll write the I'll write the
equations for these things in a moment
but this is what a uniformly accelerated
reference is the closest thing that
there is to a uniformly accelerated
reference frame each one of these
observers sees something going on which
is time
independent it sure looks like it's time
dependent looks like it's going faster
over here but what they feel in their
own rest frame is identical all along
the trajectory but does this one feel
the same as this one as the same as this
one as the same same as this one
no you can see
that from the circle analogy from the
circle
analogy
imagine a family of
observers moving in circular
orbits all attached to the same uh rigid
rods
here would these observers all see the
same
acceleration no who gets the biggest
acceleration on the one on the inside
you make a tight turn and it's a bigger
acceleration uh am I right did I get it
right
yeah yeah right more curved on the uh on
the inside here than the outside okay
actually the right the right thing to be
thinking about is uniform velocity not
the if it was the same velocity they all
have the same velocity that's the
appropriate analogy not that they're
attached to Sticks this way
uh yeah they all have the same velocity
they all move with the same velocity
that corresponds to the well okay that's
that's the right thing to do all right
these observers see different
accelerations not with time but with
where they are along here in fact the
deeper in you go the larger the
acceleration of these
observers the acceleration in fact is is
basically one over the distance from the
origin one over the proper distance from
the origin is the acceleration that's
the closest thing that there is in
special relativity to the concept of a
uniformly accelerated reference
frame you might not you might ask why
not just take one of these uniformly
accelerated guys
which is a hyperbola and then take
another hyperbola displaced from it by
the Same by a given distance so that
each one is sort of parallel to the
other and they all experience the same
acceleration what what happen these this
would be a very odd coordinate
[Music]
system
uh the reason being the distance
between each
neighboring Observer would change with
time why is that because things are in
my frame of reference standing here I've
kept the distance fixed this distance is
the same as this distance is the same as
this distance but what happens in the
reference frames which are
accelerating in the reference frames
which are accelerating the moving
observers see these points get further
and further apart so that's not a good
definition of an accelerated reference
frame this is the best that you can do
all right and notice that it has the
feature as you get closer and closer to
the center here the acceleration goes up
and up and
up another way to say it is that people
moving on these
trajectories experience effective
gravitational fields why because
acceleration and gravity have the same
effect on things so if we had an
elevator over heat that was being
accelerated this way and another one
over here being accelerated this way and
another one being over here accelerated
this way they would experience different
gravitational fields larger and larger
and
larger until you got to The Observer who
was at such a small distance here that
they have an enormous acceleration as
they go around this Bend as they go
around this Bend IN SpaceTime there's an
enormous acceleration in a very small
amount of time proper time from here to
here the velocity has changed a great
deal get even
closer and on in an even smaller
distance the velocity changes a lot
smaller amount of time so these ones are
the ones that are maximally accelerated
these ones out here have a very
negligible
acceleration that's constant
acceleration constant along the
trajectory but not constant from
Observer to Observer so effectively what
we have here is a series of people in in
this reference frame series of people
separated by fixed
distances but each one as you go down
the line feeling a stronger and stronger
gravitational
field the one in here is experiencing an
enormous gravitational
field uh because he's so highly
accelerated the one out here experiences
a very negligible gravitational field or
you can think of it as a sequence of
acceler not
elevators where the elevator lowest down
very close to here is experiencing a
very large acceleration the elevator up
high is accelerating with a small
acceleration and so in this kind of
geometry in special relativity there
really is no such thing as a uniform
gravitational field this gravit the
effective gravitational field from the
equivalence principle the effective
gravitational field for a uniformly
accelerated Observer becomes infinite at
that point now there's nothing happening
there nothing special happening there
this is flat SpaceTime it's just that
we're accelerating these
observers somebody is giving them rocket
ships or doing
something uh to accelerate these
Observers
maybe in this picture of course X
corresponds to the vertical direction of
space
t being the vertical direction of
SpaceTime is not the direction that
elevators move in these elevators are
moving horizontally so that's the
vertical
Direction what
happens supposing this Observer who is
being accelerated he's being accelerated
a rope is pulling him okay a rope is
pulling him and causing him to
accelerate or a rocket is accelerating
him some thrust is causing him to
accelerate and move down the
trajectory what happens if this
Observer out of his rocket ship drops a
rock or anything else what does that
rock do it is not connected to the
accelerating device it's not connected
to the Rockets it's not connected to the
cables that are pulling the uh what does
it
do it moves in a straight
line it moves in a straight line down
right it's going down from one
hyperboloid to the
next and eventually passes through that
point over
there so when he throws this rock out of
the rocket ship let's say he just drops
it just drops it doesn't throw it just
drops it so the rock is moving with the
same velocity as the spaceship over
here just drops the rock out out but of
course the rock is not being accelerated
so the spaceship is being accelerated
away from the rock but from the
observer's point of view the rock is
falling where is it falling toward it's
falling from one hyperbola to the next
hyperbola to the next and so it's
falling down it's falling down uh into
this region of enormously large
acceleration is it getting accelerated
no but does it look like it's getting
accelerated relative to these observers
sure so this object what's that it also
takes forever well we're going to see
that it takes forever yes we're going to
see it takes
forever well we have to we have to
Define these time sections
correctly okay but before we do we can
get a general picture of what's going on
now there's one other thing which is
kind of interesting think of all these
observers think of this rock passing
here this is a very special kind of rock
it's a musical
rock well maybe and it's a special kind
of music it's uh carried by light waves
instead of sound waves all right so it's
flashing music uh and uh sending out
light rays The Observer over here let's
draw him more clearly let's get rid of
this rock over
here this rock which falls through over
here the musical rock over here sends
out light rays
and this Observer over here experiences
them okay but once he has passed
through this point here this light cone
here no signal that he ever sends will
ever get to this
Observer no signal from here will ever
get out past this like cone that's the
Restriction that nothing moves faster
than the speed of light so any signal
that this rock
SS will never get out to The Observers
out
here this geometry has what is called or
this geometry or this coordinate system
has what is called an event
horizon this now there's no black hole
around there's not even anything
gravitating there's just a uniformly
accelerated coordinate
system musical rocks which fall through
the light cone here because they move in
straight lines but from
outside once that rock has passed Once
the musical Rock has passed the
um
the light cone or the lightlike surface
here it's gone it's gone it cannot uh it
cannot report any activity beyond that
point it might might help to notice that
The Rock actually isn't moving the only
thing that's happening is the time is
elapsing on the rock well it might be
moving but it also might be not moving
in the
EXA that's correct it wouldn't be moving
in the stationary reference frame yeah
let's draw that more accurately that's
correct it's not if it happened to be
let off the ship at exactly this point
here where the hyperboloid was vertical
it would just move up straight and in
our reference frame where we're drawing
this picture The Rock would be standing
still okay and it might be emitting
signals those signals would go up but
once it passes this point it can no
longer send any signal to what I'll
think of as the outside world now we'll
think of this as the outside world and
we'll think of this as some place behind
an event horizon question yeah at this
point is is the origin there is that
arbitrary or is the origin of yeah the
or the origin but right right right but
let's we think I'm thinking of these as
real material observers not just a
coordinate frame for a moment but real
material observers connected by meter
sticks uh watching what's going
on the origin is right well of
course this Observer over here could
always decide at some moment to
disconnect
himself from the accelerating device and
just fall through and make contact with
this that's fine but no Observer who
stays on the outside no Observer who
makes sure that he stays to the right of
this light cone who doesn't allow
himself to fall through that light cone
can ever get a signal from behind here
so that's the yeah uh wouldn't The Rock
move in a path that's that's sort of
tangent to the hyperbola over here it
has a increasing uh x with time if it
was dropped off right at this time okay
let's see dropped off later if it was
dropped off later yes it would move this
way an angle like that yes but it would
still pass this light cone because it's
moving slower than the speed of light
yeah so at some point it would pass this
point of no return shall we call
it sign yes the rock can still get
signals from the outside
right the rock can get signals from the
outside right so the Horizon is a kind
of
oneway door or oneway um membrane I
don't know what to call it oneway filter
H one way mirror one way what mirror One
Way well no it's not a mirror I don't
think it's a mirror to anybody nobody
sees anything reflected off
it uh it's it's just a oneway that's
all oneway door a doorway to uh
okay now let's um let's actually write
some coordinates I'm going to actually
tell you in detail what the coordinate
transformation
is qu was there a question from the
ordinary reference frame to The
uniformly Accelerated one questions no
questions
good is it clear what's going on in that
picture I think it's pretty clear and
this is kind of the quintessential
example of a
horizon and uh one of the interesting
things that you can see about the
Horizon is that for somebody who falls
through it nothing special happens it's
just a nonevent where whereas from the
person from the
outside they're seeing something rather
peculiar and we'll try to figure out
what it is that they see peculiar as the
uh as The Rock Rides on its
trajectory okay let's go back to circles
for a
minute here's
circles here's X and instead of calling
this T I'll call it y but notice that Y
is a great deal like time
here right what is the coordinate
transformation from Polar coordinates to
or from X and Y to Polar
coordinates that's the relationship in
fact between the accelerated reference
frame and the ordinary reference frame
the ordinary reference frame is like X
and Y and the accelerated reference
frame is more like polar coordinates
okay so the polar coordinates here are R
and Theta Theta is angle and it sweeps
you along a
circle as Theta varies keeping R fixed
you stay on a circle but you sweep along
it that sounds awfully much like staying
on a hyperbola and sweeping along
it so Theta must be something like time
along this trajectory here because it
varies along the circle but doesn't vary
as you go in and
out okay what's the connection between x
y r and Theta I think we've done this
more than
once X
is R cosine
Theta and Y
is R sin
Theta and notice that X2 + Y2
= R
2 that's because cosine s + sin 2 =
1 okay what's the
relationship over
here the relationship is almost
identical except that you replace SS and
cosiness with hyperbolic angles now do
we all know what hyperbolic uh signs and
cosiness are we do don't we we've
learned it
before we learned it in the fall we
learned it in the fall good so at least
at least some of us will remember and
remember all right the answer is x
equals we can take we can use the
coordinate R again and R just tells us
which one of these hyperboloids we on it
tells us how at the at the moment of
closest approach over here it tells us
how far we are from the
origin that's the same r appears over
here but instead of theta I'm not going
to call it Theta I'm going to give it
another name I'm going to call it Omega
and I'm going to write R hyperbolic
cosine of
Omega and Y
equals
R
cinch
Omega Omega is a thing which varies
along
here let's see what it is at this point
over here is Ral 1 what is and let's
call this now Omega equal
0 this is Omega = 1 this would be Omega
= 2 and so forth this would be Omega
equal minus
one and Omega is the thing which The
Observer along here experiences as a
kind of time it varies from here to here
to here to here
it varies from here to here to here to
here hyperbolic cosine what does
hyperbolic cosine range over from what
to what or what does Omega range
over minus infinity to plus infinity
hyper hyperbolic angles are not like
ordinary angles they don't go from 0 to
2 pi and come back to themselves they
vary from Omega equals minus infinity
way down here so this Observer coming in
from a long way off starts at Omega
equal minus
infinity comes up and then goes back out
and eventually is Omega plus infinity so
Omega equals plus infinity is way way
out here on the ends of the hyperboloids
the ASM tootes of the hyperboloid Omega
equal Z is over here and this is the
coordinate transformation to hyperbolic
to um accelerated coordinate system I
don't call this T it is the time
[Music]
that the accelerated coordinate Observer
will
use okay I don't call it t because we've
already called T something else so Omega
is a kind of
time notice that it does vary in a Tim
likee
Direction it doesn't vary As you move
horizontally it moves at least over here
varies As you move
vertically okay that's the why is that
in t sorry T my mistake
t
t my
mistake
okay right that's the coordinate
transformation and what about the other
two coordinates of
space z and
y different y different y not that y
just the other two coordinates of space
Y and Z what do we do with
them
nothing that has to do with the fact
that if you're if you're Lauren
transformed along a given Direction the
perpendicular coordinates don't
change all right so as this fellow is
being
accelerated uh the and he has meter
sticks oriented in the direction
perpendicular to the acceleration
nothing happens to to then okay so Y and
Z nothing happens
to that's the uniformly accelerated
reference
frame and
this is the Event Horizon for the
uniformly accelerated reference frame
what else do we have to say about
this
uh I wanted to say something else about
this oh yeah let's work out the metric
the metric of flat space now we're
talking about flat
space all right this is flat space time
but I want to write its metric in terms
of R and K
Omega okay uh we can do this in a number
of ways let's just root force it what is
DX DX is equal to Dr * cos
Omega plus r * the derivative of C Omega
which is cinch
Omega time D
Omega all I've done here was write that
the differential of a product is the
differential of the first Factor times
the second plus the second Factor times
the differential of the first and the
differential of K Omega is cinch Omega D
Omega
what about
DT DT is equal to Dr cinch
Omega
plus
r cos Omega D Omega I've used the fact
that the differential of cinch Omega is
C
Omega now let's calculate the metric we
know what the metric is the metric is DT
^2 minus dx2 right flat space time
I'm not even going to worry about Y and
Y and Z they just go along for the ride
so let's write down the metric d^2 = DT
^2 minus dx2 okay let's see what we
get from dt^ 2 we're going to get a Dr
SAR so first of all we'll get a Dr 2 but
then from dx2 we'll also get a Dr R 2
term and what are we going to get we're
going to get the r 2
times let's see I got to be careful here
I'll get
the yeah I'll get I got to keep my
negative sign straight
[Music]
um uh DT squ d t^2 = dt^ 2 yeah we're
okay we're okay okay so good so what do
I get from the two terms with the Dr s
we'll get sin squ minus cos squ right
sin squ - cos
2 what's sin s - cos
squ sure it's not minus
one I think it's minus
one
so we get the r
SAR with a minus
sign now we're going to get another term
with a d Omega
squar that one's going to have cos squ
minus sin squ there's an R here cos squ
- sin squ what's cos s- sin
S one but we're also going to have an r
s so there's going to be+ R 2 D Omega
s and then there's going to be some
other terms there's going to be a term
for example from dt^ 2 here we'll have a
term with Dr R * D
Omega a cross term in the metric but
let's look at it what's it going to have
it's going to have cin Omega cos Omega *
r
well there going to be a cross term from
here K Omega cinch Omega * R the two
cross terms are the same except that
we're subtracting DT ^2 from dx2 the
result is they cancel there are no cross
terms this is the
metric this is the
metric of flat space
time in uniformly accelerated coordinate
system
that a uniformly accelerated coordinate
system should be thought of as only
covering the part out
here doesn't cover the doesn't cover the
region in here we can we can make it
cover the region in here but think of it
as R greater than
zero this is the metric and it's the
metric that describes everything in this
uniform accelerated reference frame
here it's flat space time it's just flat
space time time but notice what it has
it has gal
1 and it has G
RR equal to
R2 incidentally the other components of
the minus r
2 sorry do
I just just just yeah yeah g Omega Omega
equals
1 G RR equals
minus no no no
no R
2 and
G RR =
minus1 this is kind of an interesting uh
metric here G Omega Omega is like the
time time component of the metric notice
that it varies like R squar it varies
and remember that g not is very much
like the Newtonian potential we have a
Newtonian potential which is growing as
we move out in
R that's the reason that Things Fall
toward the
origin they fall towards the origin
because the time time component of the
metric which is like the gravitational
potential is increasing
as we go away from the origin so in this
accelerated coordinate system where G KN
is not just equal to
one but where it varies with distance
there's an effective force on an object
which is pushing it toward the uh toward
R equals
z so that's everything there is to know
I think about the uniformly accelerated
coordinate
system there's another name for this
region of SpaceTime over here when it's
described in terms of these coordinates
it's called rindler space rindler
space I don't know why it's called
rindler space I presume rindler was the
first one to he's certainly not the
first one to have studied
it but uh his name got attached to it he
did something I'm not sure what um but
uh
that's the uniformly coordin uh uniform
acceleration coordinate system and
rindless space has a horizon that's what
makes it interesting I I have read
that this rler quadrant or uniformly
accelerated FR
are subset of mow Spas well it's
obviously a subset of Makowski space
that's a quadrant of
it what is the GE
well that's okay
good first of all what does it look like
in uh in here's a
geodesic okay what does it look like in
R and Omega well R equals z is not is is
not just a point over here R equals Zer
R very very tiny R very tiny is this
whole hyperboloid which is very close to
the L cone the whole L cone can be
thought of R equals 0 or it's an
extension of R equals 0 all right so
what happens is the particle pops out of
R equals 0 Let's plot its motion or
let's draw its
motion now let's plot Omega omeg
GA and
R Omega and R these are the coordinates
in the accelerated reference frame okay
so let's start at Omega equals this is
Omega equals minus infinity Omega way
way down here is Omega equals minus
infinity which means from this point of
view the very remote
past very remote past is incoming ASM
totic hyperbolas the particle comes in
crosses R equals 0 so long in the past
it's at R equals
0 it pops out it pops out and goes all
the ways out to R equals let's say
1 it pops out goes to R equals 1 turns
around and falls back
in that's what happens over here
it's gone from the remote past to the
remote
future jumped out in the remote past
gone through some Maximum
R in other words it's in a gravitational
field there's a gravitational field
pulling everything that way you threw it
out when the remote passed it jumped out
and fell back in it never crossed
crossed R equals 0 well I say it never
crossed you say sure it crossed R equals
0 it crossed R equals 0 over here but
what rindler time does that correspond
to this Omega is called the rindler time
it corresponds to Omega equals minus
infinity so from the point of view of
the accelerated reference
frame The Observer sees the particle
jump
out and the very very remote past and
then fall back in
once it's falling back in can't see it
anymore but at what point in time does
it fall back in over
here Omega Omega Omega time equals
infinity so from the perspective of this
Observer here in his coordinate system
it never passes through the Horizon over
here it just takes an infinite amount of
Omega time to see it pass through the
origin uh or to have it pass through the
origin in
fact an observer out here can never see
it pass through here any observer looks
back and sees the particle no matter how
late he looks back he always sees the
particle on the outside of the
Horizon so what somebody outside
sees when we drop a rock through the
Horizon sees it just go slow slower and
slower and slower and take an infinite
amount of his time to pass through the
Horizon yeah what
the Rock SE if he looks out nothing very
special he uh he looks
out and he does see these hyperboloids
these hyperbolas receding away from him
all right but he can see him well let's
see sorry uh no he
uh well let's redraw the picture let's
redraw the picture
to make it a little bit clearer I've got
too many things on it
already
yeah I drew that yeah I drew it the
wrong way let's let's redraw
it okay so the rock goes through here's
the
hyperbola now the rock cannot send the
sign to the outside tries to send the
signal to the outside it will not go out
but it can receive signals from the
outside so this
Observer can send a
signal that the Falling Rock will
detect yeah whatever yeah in other words
this rock will have no difficulty seeing
this observer in fact he will see him
recede away from him you know you know
the later over here he looks back sees
him moving practically with the same
velocity over here he looks back and he
sees him moving away a little later time
looks back and sees him moving away a
little bit
faster
but as long as he lasts he will look
back and be able to see all of the
observers on the outside every single
one of them but the observers on the
outside cannot receive signals from
him so he can absorb signals detect
signals get information from the outside
but cannot send it back out on the other
hand from the outside observers the
outside means the rindler space here
from the outside observer's
perspective watching this rock fall
let's watch let's have him watch I wish
we had more colors we've run out of
colors all right so here's the Observer
let's get rid of some spe
lines and how does he watch how do you
watch you watch by collecting light
signals from things all right collecting
light signals from The Rock means
looking
back along a backward lightlike
Direction looks back and sees the rock
over here goes a little further sees the
rock over here goes a little further
sees the rock over here but keeping in
mind that this hyperboloid here ASM
tootes to the ly
cone as time goes to the very remote
future for the accelerated Observer all
he sees is the rock get closer and
closer to the Horizon never passing it
yeah this so special relativity this is
all special relativity but in
accelerated coordinate systems right now
what should we find about a gravitating
mass we should find something about a
gravitational mass that looks like this
yeah and we
will paradoxal that the accelerated
Observer kind of appears is is is
missing from a great bit of the history
of the rock I mean until the rock
actually passes the lower acid blue sh
he can't he can't see the at Observer
The Accelerated Observer doesn't
exist sign from the P yeah yeah but
there's no accelerated observer in that
past only when
cross so
some yes that's the
[Music]
of so at some time the obser the the
Rock The Rock The Rock suddenly sees
from very very far away he sees the
Observer coming in it's created at that
time so speak effectively created at
that
time and uh and then sees coming start
seeing start seeing come in with a huge
velocity coming in with long if you
really can see him that would mean that
this person was sending poons
if he was really sending photons and he
was moving with closer the speed of
light relative to the rock of course he
would be sending very very blue shifted
photons right so he get a
blast of radiation from the air at this
point uh but uh when
I okay on the other hand the Observer
out
here sees the Rock and sees radiation
from The Rock getting red shifted
because he's moving away from the rock
so he sees what he sees is the rock
moving slower and slower to the Horizon
never get quite getting there and
getting all of the signals progressively
more and more red shifted that's the
nature of of our m
space
what I'm not going to do is to write
down Einstein's equations and solve them
it's a real
mess uh to write them down we have would
have first have to work out the
curvature tensor which means the
christopal symbols and then
differentiate them and then multiply
them together and then contract them to
make the Einstein
tensor and it is a big long
mess somebody has done it for
us uh there are ways to do it which are
more sophisticated and clever
where you can see what the answer is
faster but with the straightforward
Brute Force methods it is a big mess and
furthermore there are a lot of Einstein
equations how many of them are there all
together
well uh n d * D minus1 over2 or
something well they're not all
independent and so it's not really that
bad really there are only two
independent ones that are um important
but they're still quite uh quite
unpleasant um what I'm going to do is to
tell you the
solution for a particular situation and
then Analyze That solution analyze the
geometry that comes from it which is far
more fun than solving the
equations now what we're trying to do is
put together something which is the
analog of a point
Mass keep in mind that in Newtonian
physics the solution for a point Mass
has a degree of generality which goes
beyond the point Mass if you have any
spherically symmetric distribution of
material and you're
outside the region that encompasses that
uh that
material then the standard Newtonian
solution of for the gravitational field
is the exactly the same as the point
particle at the center the same is true
in general relativity in uh in nutonian
physics I believe it's just called
Newton's theorem in general relativity
it's called birkoff's theorem b i r k FF
berkoff's theorem what burkoff proved
was that any spherically symmetric
distribution of material which is
bounded outside the boundary of the
material the metric is exactly the same
as the metric of a black hole you could
think of to some extent the metric of a
black hole as being the analog of the
metric of the point particle although
although it is hardly Point particle is
in any ordinary sense of the the
word okay
so I'm simply going to write the answer
down and we'll look at it and some
pieces of it will recognize
will recognize everything about it but
some pieces will recognize why they are
the way they are other pieces I will
simply have to tell you but before I do
that I want to write down flat
SpaceTime in polar coordinates now not
these polar coordinates these are the
polar coordinates of space not polar
coordinates of SpaceTime but just
ordinary polar coordinates of space
let's just start with space now we've
written polar coordinates for space many
times but now I'm talking about
three-dimensional polar coordinates not
two-dimensional polar
coordinates we have three-dimensional
space now this is ordinary space now not
space time three-dimensional ordinary
space and I want to describe it in polar
coordinates what does polar coordinates
mean what are polar coordinates mean it
means that you describe every
Point as being at a certain distance
from the origin R having nothing to do
with the RS that I might have written
earlier over here doesn't have to do
with this forget that we're now
concentrating on threedimensional
Space just put into your notes now that
I have changeed not well maybe I should
call it capital r perhaps if I called it
capital r it might be less confusing
let's call it capital r distance from
the
origin
no
oh
curvature I think it's less I I don't
think you're in too much danger of
confusing a coordinate with a curvature
but you might confuse this coordinate
with that one so I won't I won't
the call it what p p over
two could call it P over let's call it R
for radius all right it's really the
radial distance from the
origin and not a single angle as you
would have in two Dimensions but rather
you think of a point on a sphere a point
on a unit sphere imagine a unit sphere
begin with a unit sphere a unit sphere
means one of radius one so it's the
earth except measured in units in which
the Earth has radius one and it takes
two angles to describe a point on the
surface of a sphere one of them the
polar angle the other the aamal angle
which would you prefer to call
Fi Fi is polar angle all right so that
means an r and a fi and a
Theta now first of all let's think about
the metric on a sphere
the metric of a sphere itself let's
begin with the unit sphere a unit sphere
of radius one what is the metric on a
unit sphere let's just call it DS squ
I'm not using D squ because I don't want
to think of it as proper time I want to
think of it as spatial distance d s s
anybody remember what it
is you said that F was polar coordinate
all right so it's d^
squ and now what are we taking Theta
we're imagining is the angle from the
equator or from the North
Pole we can either make
uh sorry wait that's this this is uh
that's this that that's are we taking
this to be the angle from the equator or
the angle from uh from the equator all
right okay so from the
equator North
Pole north pole angle from the North
Pole okay if it's angle from the North
Pole then we get s squar Theta d^ 2 and
I'm not going to explain that I'm going
to let you work that out that's the
that's the metric on a
sphere
okay what's
that D Theta ah the Theta
squar
no wait what I'm sorry what's the
definition of the Polar angle is it the
angle from the pole the angle from the
pole the angle from the pole okay so
from the Ang that that's F right we said
that's F
yeah oh sin squ F good getting tired I'm
getting tired sin squ 5 D Theta squ sin
squ good do I have it right yes good all
right so here's the North Pole f is
measured relative to the North Pole and
Theta is measured around the
Equator this is the metric of a unit
sphere now supposing the sphere has
radius R what do we do with
it we just multiply it by R squ every
length is R SAR time every squared
length is R 2times bigger than it would
be on the unit sphere
so it just
becomes R
times
d 5^ 2 + S of 5^ 2ar the Theta
squ H did I get it wrong
again yeah yeah not yet not yet this is
this is the Met yeah yeah you're right
this is the metric on the sphere
itself all right so that's the metric
between points on a sphere of radius R
now what happens if I want to talk talk
about points which are not on the same
radius then I have to include
here D s^2 equals the
R2 plus
that in other words for Mo for points
which are separated by radial distance
it's just the r
s and that for points which are
separated by angles it's R 2 times the
metric on the unit sphere there's
another way to write this which
everybody usually which you know is
common is to write it d s s is equal to
d r 2 + r
2 D Omega
squar D Omega squar is a shorthand for
writing out the metric on the unit
sphere so Omega D Omega squar is a
shorthand that uh that's convenient if
we don't want to keep writing thetas and
fi that's the metric
of ordinary flat
space
uh in spherical polar coordinates and
remember now that Omega stands for two
directions Theta and F and the r squar
here is just uh there because as you go
further and further out the sphere just
gets bigger and bigger that's all okay
that's uh that's now what about space
time time supposing we're doing flat
space time this is the metric of
space it really is equal to just good
old dx2 + D Y2 + dz^2
that's all it is in some other
coordinates X Y and
Z but what about the metric of SpaceTime
the metric of
SpaceTime which is D to squared let's
let's put it over here the to
squared is equal Al
to let's call it dt^
2 minus dx^ 2us d y^ 2us dc^
2 right that's where did the C's go if
we wanted to put speeds of light in I
think they would go over
here if we wanted to put speeds of light
in they would go over
there I'll include them a little bit for
the moment how do we rewrite that in in
the polar coordinates well we just
rewrite it as d^ 2 = DT ^2 minus exactly
what we see
here the R
2 plus r
2 the minus r 2 D Omega
2 and I'm not going to if I wanted to
put the speeds of light in they would go
in here in the denominator DT ^2 minus
Dr R 2 - r^ 2 D Omega
2 that's the metric of absolutely flat
SpaceTime just using spherical polar
coordinates the Schwarz Shield metric
being the metric of a spherical
distribution of mass is conveniently
described
in spherical coordinates like this when
you have a problem with the symmetry of
a sphere it's always convenient to use
polar coordinates
right if you use polar coordinates then
I'm now going to write down the metric
and I'll tell you what uh what goes into
it this is the solution it's a
solution of Einstein's
equations with any spherically
symmetric let's
say energy distribution do
T with any spherically symmetric
distribution of energy and M of
energy right outside the boundaries of
that region so here's the region and we
look outside the region the general
solution outside the
region
uh has the following
form d^
s
equals one you know what before I do
this this let me remind you about the
Newtonian solution the Newtonian
solution of course is in terms of a
gravitational potential now we're going
to get into trouble gravitational
potential is called
fi because it's like an angle it's not
like an
angle gravitational potential is capital
fi right gravitational poti IAL is
gravitational F and what's the solution
of Newton's equations for a point Mass
it's just f
equals the mass of the gravitating
object
G divided
r with a minus sign or a plus sign I
can't remember uh minus sign
right right minus
sign
that's because it's it's attractive it
pulls you towards the origin okay now
remember what the what the connection
between G KN and F is G
not at least
approximately is equal to a
constant let's write it
out is equal to some
constant when I say constant it's a
piece which doesn't have a derivative
and and then the piece which has the
derivative is supposed to be plus is it
5 /
2 or is it two
two two my mistake
two that was the connection that we
discovered several times in discussing
motion of particles that the motion of a
particle connects G not or in in
relativistic theory G not replac F or at
least its derivatives do there's a
factor of two there and an additive
constant which doesn't matter when you
differentiate it okay that's GN so we
would like now to write the metric we'll
start with some dt^ 2 it's the thing
which
replaces the coefficient one over here
flat space time has a coefficient
one
let's see what it has to have it's going
to be G not not and what I expect is it
will have the form some
constant plus twice 5 period but f is
just minus mg /
R now that may or may not be
exact happens that it is
exact
minus there a factor of two and so it's
minus 2 mg over
R now what shall I take this constant C
to
be well let's go very very far from the
black hole this is a black hole of
Stellar Mass we go 75 billion trillion
zillion
uh
uh light years away from it we don't see
it right I mean it's it's it's a
negligible perturbation on our geometry
and our geometry originally was just dt^
squ with a one there only one thing this
could be it's got to be
one very far from the black hole when R
is extremely large this is
negligible when R is extremely big and
we have to go over to what uh to what
would be just flat space so it's got to
be
one this term
here is is unaffected this is the
angular part on the sphere it turns out
when you work out the equations turns
out no effect on it just exactly the
same so minus r^
2 The Omega
squar and this term is also slightly
affected in a manner similar to this
one this is the hard part this this is
actually not so hard to show that this
one's unaffected this one was easy easy
we just use the correspondence between G
and 2 pi the hard one which requires the
extra labor of solving Einstein's
equations is this 1 divided by 1 - 2 mg
/
R Dr R
2 now
again when you go far away from the
black hole or from the it doesn't have
to be black hole when you go far away
from the
mass R becomes large 2 mg over R becomes
small one just stays there and this just
becomes one so it goes right over to
this formula
here but there are two Corrections one
in the t^2 and one in the r s they're
identical except one occurs in the
denominator and one occurs in the
numerator that is not an accident
but it's not something I can easily
explain without spending some time going
through the
uh uh going through the equations but
it's good enough we don't we don't
really need to this is a nice
structure let's see if I put the speeds
of light in let's see if we can figure
out where they would
go uh let's figure out what the units of
capital G
are all right so uh this you know let's
figure out the units of capital gr R
force is equal to mass SAR G / R right
no energy energy is mass squ G /
r i don't literally mean equals although
it I mean the same units okay so what's
the energy what's the units of energy
units of energy are mass time velocity
squar let's use c^ 2 as units of mass
mass time velocity squared where C has
units of velocity because it's the speed
of light and that's got to equal m^2 G /
R so we cancel out a
m we divide by this M over
here and we multiply by r
so whatever G is it has units of length
velocity squared divided
m
h did I get it wrong no oh okay I think
I got it
right uh I'll just call this r capital
r all right now twice mg over R it has
to have the same dimensions as one
because you can add something with
different dimensions to something else
but it doesn't if I work out let's let's
see what we have um from uh from this
equation over here I can see that mg
over R has units of the speed of light
squared C I need a c squ in the
denominator yeah no we don't want to put
the C squ here because we want to match
on the flat space time okay okay so we
don't want to put the C squ there all
right now um that same c^ s has to go
over
here but let's put let's put back our C
squ our original C squ here there's a c
s
here uh that means there's another C squ
downstairs here if I put back all the C
squares I believe it would look like
that that's what it would look
like
right
notice that um the speed of light down
in here makes this very very
small so it's a very small perturbation
on the metric this is characteristic um
don't expect that an ordinary Mass like
the sun is going to make tremendously
big perturbations on the structure of
the metric it won't space is not highly
deformed near the sun even though the
sun has a large mass and there and
there's a significant gravitational
potential of the Sun but it doesn't
translate into a large deformation
because of the C squ downstairs all
right so the C squ is what keeps
uh the geometry around the Sun from
looking highly
curved all right so that's that's the
Schwarz Shield metric this is the whole
metric of a black
hole
and it's the simplest of black holes
it's not rotating it doesn't have any
electric charge but it has all the basic
features that we're going to
explore uh the next time what I'm going
to show
you is how similar this metric it
doesn't look anything like it but how
similar the metric of the black hole is
to the metric of rindler space let me
just write it down for you
again
R 2 The Omega SAR minus the R 2 well
it's a different R different
r r 2 The Omega 2 minus the R 2 that was
minus the x^2 minus d y uh minus D z^2
minus d
y^2
right looks very very different doesn't
look anything like it we're going to
find out that the Horizon of the black
hole
is very very similar to The Horizon of
the rindler space and that's going to be
our goal that really will carry us
through uh through the
quarter so as I said our next our main
goal is going to be to understand the
Horizon of this black hole from this
point of view you can't even see that it
has a
horizon any questions before we
leave
[Music]
the preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University please visit us at
stanford.edu